<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A boke made by a certayne great clerke, agaynst the newe idole, and olde deuyll whiche of late tyme, in Misnia shulde haue ben canonysed for a saynt.</title>
            <title>Wider den neuen Abgott un alten Teufel, der zu Meissen soll erhoben werden English</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1534</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16962</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106355</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842073</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6697</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6697)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 738:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A boke made by a certayne great clerke, agaynst the newe idole, and olde deuyll whiche of late tyme, in Misnia shulde haue ben canonysed for a saynt.</title>
                  <title>Wider den neuen Abgott un alten Teufel, der zu Meissen soll erhoben werden English</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[Imprynted by me Robert Wyer dwellynge in saynt Martyns parysshe, besydes charynge Crosse],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1534]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Luther, Martin.  Wider den neuen Abgott un alten Teufel, der zu Meissen soll erhoben werden.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>Leaf E7v: Thus endeth the worke made agaynst the false canonysacyon of Benno the Bysshope.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Benno II, --  Bishop of Osnabrück, 1020?-1088 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:1"/>
            <p>A boke made by a certayne great clerke, agaynſt the newe Idole, and olde Deuyll / whiche of late tyme, in Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia ſhulde haue ben canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for a ſaynt. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <p>☞☜</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of a clerk writing on his lap in the country outside a city</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſte of all I do make pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtacyon, that in this boke myne in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent is not that Benno the byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope, which is deed many yeres ago / ſhulde eyther be iudged or els condempned. For he hath his iudge, lyke as al other haue / whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che haue departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this lyfe: of whome it is not laufull for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man to pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or gyue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, oneles it be ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god hathe peraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture reueled it vnto hym. Fyrſt by wordes, &amp; afterwardes by ſygnes / for we do onely here touche &amp; rebuke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lyuynge Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,
<note place="margin">Satan.</note> which nowe in this tyme (in which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goſpell is agayne ryſen vp by the grace of god, &amp; ſhineth all abrode) knoweth none other <pb facs="tcp:6697:3"/>way howe to auenge hym ſelfe / than vnto the ſcornynge of god, and to the rebuke and ſclaunder of his worde, to take vnto hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe ſuche maner diſguyſed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parayle / that vnder the name of Benno, (whiche forſothe wolde more gladlye haue reſted in his graue) he myght ſuffre hym ſelfe with great ordynaunce of golde and ſyluer and with ſolempne and royall pompe to be conſecra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and worſhypped for a ſaynt. But the Ire and wrathe of god worketh this, and bryngeth it to paſſe, that thoſe obſtynate and blynde tyrauntes and purſuers (ſuche as is the Pope with his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes) which do not receyue,
<note place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe.</note> no nor yet can ſuffre the goſpell vnto theyr owne ſaluacyon: are compelled to beleue leaſynges &amp; great errours, and the diſceytes <pb facs="tcp:6697:3"/>of the deuyll,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſa. ſecundo.</note> As Paule ſaythe vnto theyr greater condempna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon. And I do this ſo moch the more gladly, and with more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mynde, for that I do knowe of a ſuretie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is nothyng plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt nor acceptable to Benno (yf it ſo be that he is a ſaynt in very dede) to be canoniſed. Lyke wyſe as it was neuer pleaſaunt to any of all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes that they haue ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope / Howe be it this ſame thynge (I meane to be canonyſed) hathe chaunſed to very fewe of them. For theſe mere Papiſtical ſaintꝭ haue ben for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt part of them no true chryſtyans, ſpecyally for this cauſe, that (as we do ſe com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menly to come to paſſe) of this canoniſacyon and conſecracyon of ſayntes, men do tourne them ſelfes from the grace of god and <pb facs="tcp:6697:4"/>from the fayth &amp; truſt in Chryſt: &amp; do leane vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merytes &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages of ſayntes. And ſo moche goodes and ryches is beſtowed vpon theyr temples, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worke of charyte towardes our neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is well nere extincte / &amp; that the ſayntes are accompted &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the ſtede of god / and ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp; ſtockes in the ſtede of our neyghbour / &amp; of the ſayd goodꝭ,<note place="margin">Images.</note> onely ſlowe belyes, &amp; ydell ſwyne are fat fedde in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples, chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and monaſteryes. Nowe to the laufull &amp; very ſayntes, there can be nothynge more pleaſaunt and acceptable: than that pure &amp; vncorrupte faythe and lyuely &amp; ſtronge charyte do indure &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynue amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge men. And for this cauſe god wold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Moyſes ſhuld be in ſuche wyſe buryed,
<note place="margin">The Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyaff of Moyſes.</note> that no man ſhuld knowe his graue: leſt <pb facs="tcp:6697:4"/>els he myght happely in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> place be worſhyhped, called vpon, and prayed vnto. Yea moreouer he dyd not ſuffre ſo moche as any honoure or worſhyp to be gyuen vnto god in any certayne place appoynted, or by any ſpirytuall name, oneles he had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded it before his owne ſelfe. For whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che cauſe alſo Ezechias dyd brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the braſen ſerpent into peces,
<note place="margin">Eſechias</note> albeit that god had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded it to be made: becauſe he dyd per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes wolde there ſet vp honour vnto god: though the falſe ꝓphetes alſo dyd often tymes crye, that it was done to the honour &amp; glorye of very god, euen lykewyſe as the Pope with his adherentes dothe nowe of this Benno. Howe moche leſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it to be ſuffered now theſe dayes, that in the newe teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,
<pb facs="tcp:6697:5"/>in the clere lyghte of the goſpell any maner honourynge or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppynge of god ſhuld be ſette vp of any mans owne wyttes &amp; deuocyon, beſyde that onely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and worſhyppe whiche he hathe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in faythe &amp; cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie,
<note place="margin">The true honour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rynge of god.</note> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> oblacyon &amp; offeryng vp of euery mans owne ſelfe, ſo as Paule dothe teche in the .xii. Chapitre to the Romanes. Fyrſt to begyn at the hygheſt, the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter went gaylye forwarde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that Satan was in Miſnia aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd &amp; ſet vp by Adryan,
<note place="margin">Adryan the .vi.</note> (whyles he lyued) his owne peculyer and ſpecyall myniſter and ſeruaunt / For albeit that he was acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pted &amp; taken to be of a certayne good &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable lyfe, (as the fame goeth of hym). Yet (as all ſuche maner Hypocrytes are wonte to be) he was the ſoreſt enemy of all <pb facs="tcp:6697:5"/>men vnto god and his worde / be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe I wyll not ſpeke here, that at Bruxelles he ſuffered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble murther to be done, and two martyrs to be made vnto Chryſt and to be taken for very ſayntꝭ, all thoughe he was ygnoraunte therof,
<note place="margin">Iohan &amp; Henry ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> and it was ſore agaynſt his wyll. For murther was com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted and done, as yf they had ben than heretykes, which in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dede they were not). For true chriſten men, &amp; thoſe in eſpecyall whiche haue any admyniſtracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in ſpirytual thynges? do ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther torment nor ſlee any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but they do onely (as Chriſt &amp; Paule teacheth) eſchewe the companye of wycked men, &amp; beware of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And thoughe neyther I oughte nor yet can iudge, what maner ende he had at his deth: yet this doubtles I may iudge, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte <pb facs="tcp:6697:6"/>he dyd amende before that he dyd departe from this lyfe, &amp; dyd reuoke or repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hym of ſuch murther. And dyd with his hert vnfaynedly fauour our goſpell: it is vndoubted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he is not free from dampnacyon. This mater no doubte of it is handeled in all poyntes after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> papiſtycall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.
<note place="margin">Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hus and Hiero<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge.</note> For lykewyſe as in the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of Conſtance, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hus, &amp; Hierome of Prage, thoſe verye ſayntes &amp; martyrs of god, were condempned and brente.
<note place="margin">Thomas de aquino the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of all hereſy.</note>And on the other ſyde Thomas de Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no the origynall fountayne and ſprynge of all Hereſye, the peſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and (as his bokes do wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ouerthrower &amp; deſtroyer of the goſpell, was canonyſed &amp; made a ſaynt. Euen ſo nowe (yf god be pleaſyd) our mayſter A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian doth at Bruxelles / he hath <pb facs="tcp:6697:6"/>
               <note place="margin">Adryan the .vi.</note>brente thoſe very ſayntes, Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and Henry: &amp; nowe on the other ſyde maketh I wotte not what of Benno a ſaynt, nay rather the very deuyl. For this is the pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyare &amp; propre worke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popes / they muſt nedes laboure aboute theſe thyngꝭ, that is to wytte, to rydde the very ſayntes out of the worlde, and to auau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; lyfte vp on hyghe counterfayte ſayntes / to condempne the worde of god, &amp; to eſtablyſſhe theyr owne doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne / &amp; than ſaye afterwardes, that this thynge dothe tourne to the honoure and glorye of god &amp; of his ſayntꝭ, lykewyſe as Chriſt dothe ſaye in the
.xvi. chapitre of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whan he ſaythe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THe tyme ſhall come y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> who ſoeuer dothe kyll you, ſhall wene that he dothe honoure and <pb facs="tcp:6697:7"/>ſeruyce vnto god. Forſothe this theyr noyſe ſhuld haue more wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy of ſylence / and pope Adryan with thoſe whiche do ſo buſelye promote and ſet forward the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyſacyon of Benno,
<note place="margin">Pope A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dryan.</note> ought, (&amp; not without great cauſe) to be hartely aſſhamed, yf there were but euen one lytle ſparke of wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome lefte in them, for that they haue not ben affrayed to put in wrytynge all thoſe holy maners and examples of Benno, and to reherſe them in the bulle, &amp; open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to publyſſhe them vnto the hole worlde, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to wytte, howe he dyd ioyne hym ſelf to Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the.
<note place="margin">Gregory the .vii. He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the vii. Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</note> vii. and toke parte w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hym agaynſt Henry the .vii. Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour / and dyd exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the Marchion of Miſnia and the Emperour alſo with hym / and than afterwardꝭ dyd ronne lyke <pb facs="tcp:6697:7"/>a falſe traytour vnto the Pope / I wolde haue ſayd went in pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymage to fulfyll his vowe. O howe worthy and ſemely a dede was this for a knyghte? For he ought of ryght to be called not onely by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of an holy byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: but alſo of an holy knight, &amp; he were worthye to be dygged vp with golden mattockes and ſpades, that he myght be all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther of redde gold. I wyll not here reherſe nor brynge forth the hyſtoryes, whiche do effectually ſhewe or declare, howe holelye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gregorye the .vii. dyd demeane hym ſelfe towardꝭ Henry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .viii.
<note place="margin">He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ry the viii.</note> doutles full lyke a traytour and a falſe diſceyuoure, yf a man do marke well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſſhyon of hym. For he dothe prouoke the ſone agaynſt the father, &amp; depoſeth hym fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Emperpall dignyte, <pb facs="tcp:6697:8"/>and ſuffered hym at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt to dye exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate: and all onely for cauſe of worldly ryches, honour and tyranny / vnto ſuche maner Pope dyd Benno conuey hym ſelfe (as the bulle doth reporte &amp; make boſt of hym) &amp; ſuch a pope as this, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fyrmed and mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in his peruerſytie &amp; wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. Neyther was there ſo moch wytte in that holy man as to perceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the pope dyd wye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedlye and wrongfully, whiche dyd ſtyrre vp the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, to whome god had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded obedyence and honoure to be gyuen. But he is ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly blynde, that he dothe ioyne hym ſelfe vnto the pope, &amp; dothe mayntayne &amp; defende his parte, and togyther with hym doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate the Emperoure and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Marchion: where as he ought <pb facs="tcp:6697:8"/>euen with the ieopardye of his owne lyfe to haue cryed agaynſt the pope, and to reſyſte and with ſtande hym / I wyll not (I ſaye) make reherſal of thoſe thynges.
<note place="margin">Thempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> And let vs graunte, that Henry had an vniuſt cauſe, &amp; the Pope a rightuous cauſe, (which thing for all that the hyſtoryes do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye:) yet doubtles this thynge can not be denyed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ceaſar em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braſyd the faythe, whiche is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the worde of god. But (as I haue ſayd) al this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyneſſe was onely for cauſe of money and ryches beſydes this for honour and tyrannyes ſake / for whiche thynges hethen men are wonte to ſtryue among them ſelfes / here in this thyng (I ſay) the pope dyd not Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelycally. For els he ought not to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſted that euyll, but to haue let <pb facs="tcp:6697:9"/>that thynge go which wolde not contynewe as Chriſt doth open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teache in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .v. chapitre of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thewe. yea more ouer all though themperour had done any thing alſo agaynſt the worde of god / yet for all that the Pope oughte to haue ſuffered / and as beynge the faythfull vycare of Chryſte his lord, he ought rather to haue ſuffered dethe in the cauſe. But here the Pope not onely dyd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſt euyll, and dyd reuenge hym ſelfe: but alſo he dyd moch euyll and moche iniurye and vexacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to his aduerſary. For he dyd ſhede ſo moche blode, &amp; he brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte in ſo moche diſcorde and de bate: that a man wolde euen ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre to rede of it. And yet dyd he not ceaſe nor take vp ſo,
<note place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pesdede.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll he dyd ſpoyle the Emperour of his auctoryte / dyd ſpoyle hym <pb facs="tcp:6697:9"/>and depryue hym of his Empy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, and of all his frendes, &amp; alſo of all his honour / fynally of his body and lyfe, yea and (aſmoche as in hym was to do) alſo of his ſoule. And with ſuche a Pope doth that holy man Benno con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire, whiche god wotte hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the goſpell euen with do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge of miracles alſo. Theſe are thoſe excellent &amp; noble vertues, for whiche he was iudged wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be dygged vp out of the grounde w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> golden ſpades, ꝑad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to thentent that we alſo ſhulde lerne by his examples to kepe the goſpell after the ſame faſſhyon. And veryly I do ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that this was the myracle &amp; vertue of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no, which dyd moſt moue and ſtyrre the ſee of Rome, and whiche was princypally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of it. For had not this ben <pb facs="tcp:6697:10"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture he ſhuld haue lyen yet ſtyll a great whyle in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. For who ſoeuer can worke ſuche a myracle that he can proue, and promote or ſette forwarde the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, the pompe, the auctorytie, &amp; the honours of the ſee of Rome, that man alone dothe more than yf he dyd rayſe vp .x. deade men, yea &amp; that though all the worlde in the meane ſeaſon ſhulde per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe togyther with body, and ſoule, ſubſtaunce and honoure. But thou Benno a pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocryte vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, howe gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly well haſt thou deſerued to be canonyſed: which couldeſt fynde in thyne hert to be partener with the Pope of ſo many horryble &amp; abhomynable ſynnes agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell / and all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon reaſon: and to charge &amp; burthayne thy ſelfe with them. But verely (as
<pb facs="tcp:6697:10"/>I do ſuppoſe) theſe vertues of Benno are but fayned &amp; forged of the Miſnianes to flatter the Pope with all, and to moue and ſtyrre hym to conſecrate and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyſe hym a ſaynte: becauſe they knowe well, that the Pope hathe not a lytle delectacion and pleaſure in ſuche maner tycke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge / and is not a lytle gladde,
<note place="margin">The amhi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and vayne gfo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryouſneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope.</note> whan he hereth ſuche maner ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be ſongen vnto hym. And for this cauſe therfore they dyd forthwith euen at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begynnynge laye theſe vertues forthe before, all myracles: that by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the Pope myght be taken &amp; made fonde / and that all thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues &amp; myracles beynge els vnparfyte, feble and of none efficacite or ſtrength in compary ſon of thoſe myracles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (alas for very ſhame) ſhuld <pb facs="tcp:6697:11"/>be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more acceptable vnto hym. Nowe yf it be ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they do worke with lyes &amp; falſe diſceytes: who can from henſforth doubte, that the canoniſacyon of this Benno is a mere diſceyte of the deuyll? ſo that nowe not Benno, but the deuyll hym ſelfe vnder the name of Benno dothe ſuffre hym ſelfe to be extolled and magnifyed as a ſaynt. And yf theſe thynges be true &amp; vnfayned: this one thyng I may boldly ſaye and affyrme, that Benno, yf he dyed hauynge knowlege hereof, and dyd not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pente hym and be ſorye for this ſynfull dede, was vndoubtedlye caſt downe hedlonge into helle. For the goſpell muſte nedes be truely, exactly, &amp; perfectly, kepte and fulfylled.
<note place="margin">The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is to be obſerued &amp; kepte.</note>For Chryſt ſayth, who ſoeuer ſhall breake one of theſe leaſte commaundementes: <pb facs="tcp:6697:11"/>he ſhalbe called leaſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heuyns.
<note place="margin">Math. v.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>WHat maner thyng than do thoſe Miſnianes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te to vs for a ſaynt? doubtles a ſtronge and an erraunte thefe, &amp; a bloode ſheder / the cauſe of all the calamyties and myſeryes of all Germanie / the enemye of the goſpel, the felowe of Antichryſt / to whome he dyd conueye hym ſelfe, and was made parte taker of his impietie and wyckednes. And this thynge may euydently be gathered of the hyghe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedynge great boſte, whiche is made in the bulle of our mayſter Adryan, of that excellent vertue,
<note place="margin">The bull of maſter Adryan.</note> and holyneſſe, whiche dyd ſhyne in Benno / what other thynge I beſeche you is meaned by theſe wordes / we do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate hym for <pb facs="tcp:6697:12"/>a ſaynt, which lyued contrary to the rule of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> goſpell, what other thynge (I ſaye) is this, than to ſaye: We Miſuianes are peuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhe, and vtterlye madde, whiche beynge diſtracte and beſyde our ſelfes do not conſidre nor marke what is the very goſpell ſelfe, or what is repugnaunt to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell / and whiche do make that thyng holy which we do prayſe / and which do boſte hym for this cauſe, that he dyd lyue &amp; demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne hym ſelfe contrary to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell? But thus ſhall our woode prelates ſtumble and fall: which do perſecute the worde of god. A lyke thyng and of the ſame forte is that noble and dely cate myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, whiche alſo is boſted in that excellent and goodly bulle, not without the great wyckedneſſe &amp; ſhame of Benno / &amp; not of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no <pb facs="tcp:6697:12"/>alone, but alſo of all them, which do make hym a ſaynt. For the bulle dothe boſte, howe boldly &amp; manfully Benno, for worldly ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ches ſake,
<note place="margin">The Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chion of Miſnia.</note> dyd rydde the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion of Miſnia out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, whiche had gyuen hym a buffet / and that ſame day tweluemonth after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſlayne, lykewyſe as he had alſo before manaſed &amp; thretened hym, that he wolde do. Here (god wotte) Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no dyd well interprete that place of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and alſo expreſſe it in his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, where Chryſt dothe ſaye:
<note place="margin">Mathe. v.</note> do good vnto them that are noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto you, and pray for them whiche do defame &amp; purſue you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>BUt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywyſe i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this bulle thou ſeeſt, that Chryſt dothe with myracles confyrme and for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tifye cleane contrary thynges to
<pb facs="tcp:6697:13"/>this doctryne, and with wordes dothe teache to ſuffre, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde with myracles doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell the contrary, to be done. O worſhypfull bulle, O goodly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyſers / whan wyll you ones be aſſhamed? but the bulle not contented ſo,
<note place="margin">The impi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>etie &amp; Bſaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemye of the Buſſe.</note> nor thynkynge it ynough that it doth extolle ſuch a blaſphemye for a myracle, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth further forthe alſo / &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of Benno a god, whan it ſayth: hereof it may eaſely be per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued, that diuyne power was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munycated to that godlye ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Almyghtye god ponyſſhe you, &amp; forfende this, you moſt vngracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous &amp; wretched blaſphemours / For here by theſe wordes they wyll that the ſayntes do worke myracles for them ſelfꝭ, and not Chryſt alone, ſo as it is redde in the .lxxi. pſalme, where it is ſayd, <pb facs="tcp:6697:13"/>whiche onely dothe worke great wonders.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>BUt go to nowe, let vs grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t here agayne, that this groſe and excedyng great lye was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; ymagyned of good Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no, to thentent to bowe and ſupple the mynde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, &amp; to tendre his herte. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſee of Rome is more moued and ſtyrred, and taketh more delectacyon &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of prynces be in any place euyll entreated &amp; ſharpely han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled, whan they haue ben bolde to laye hande vpon ſpirptuall goodes: than of the hole worlde were made holye. And therfore they haue alſo heaped togyther, and repeted in ſo many lege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and examples and bokes thoſe thinges, whiche dyd appertayne vnto this matter: to thentente <pb facs="tcp:6697:14"/>doubtles, that they myghte pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe and gette vnto them ſelfe plenty of goodes and pleaſures in this worlde / &amp; that they ſhuld not be conſtrayned to obſerue &amp; kepe or fulfyll the goſpell. And yf this thynge be true: than (I ſaye) this agayne that Benno is none other wyſe a ſaint, than are Annas &amp; Cayphas:
<note place="margin">Annas. Cayphas.</note> oneles per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture he toke repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his dethe for his lyfe afore ledde / And they do not a lytle diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>honoure and ſhame to Benno: whiche do boſte and openly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte ſuche dedes of hym. For yf thoſe thyngs be true, which they do carye about and boſte in the bulle: than is Benno one of the deuylles ſayntes. And yf they be but fayned thinges: than are they with theyr conſecracyon &amp; canoniſacyon all togyther mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <pb facs="tcp:6697:14"/>and ſtyrred and ruled by the deuyll. For where it may be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath not lyued accordynge to the rule and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of the ſcrypture: without doubt that man can not be holy, neyther oughte he of ryght to be conſecrated and canonyſed for a ſaynt / no thoughe he dyd rayſe vp all deed men, and dyd worke all maner myracles.
<note place="margin">The goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</note> The goſpel is more mighty &amp; of more ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth to condempne a man, than any maner ſygnes and myracles are to make hym a ſaynt. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell can neyther erre ne lye: but myracles do often tymes decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue,
<note place="margin">Suſpecte myracles.</note> as Paule hathe ſhewed vnto vs, wytneſſynge that Antichryſt ſhulde worke with falſe cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte myracles, that he myghte alſo begyle euen the verye electe perſones / and as Moyſes alſo <pb facs="tcp:6697:15"/>doth wryte in the .xiii. chapitre of Deuteronomium, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no credence ſhuld be gyuen to miracles, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the thynge ſemeth to be agaynſt the worde of god. For myracles ought to ſerue the worde, and to folowe it: &amp; not to go before it, &amp; to do preiudyce vnto it / wherfore it is neceſſary and muſt nedes be that eyther the doctrine of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no be approued, or els that his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, be of no wayght nor va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue,
<note place="margin">Myracles to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> as it is wrytten in the laſte chapytre of Mathewe. Confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng the worde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they preached with ſygnes &amp; myracles folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge / he ſaythe not with myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles goynge before, or els myra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles apperyng w<hi rend="sup">e</hi>out any worde. And moche lyke vnto theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, is that alſo, where it is ſaid, that Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no many yeres ago euen after his dethe, dyd for tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <pb facs="tcp:6697:15"/>goodes ſake poniſſhe Wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyam Marchion / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wytte beynge moued at the peticyon and prayer of a certayne mayſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or prouoſt,
<note place="margin">Wyllyam the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion of Miſnia.</note> dyd ſtryke out the Marchions iye (as for the moſt parte holye are wonte to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of churches collegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate). For theſe noble prelates do all that euer maye be done for moneys ſake, and for cauſe of ambicyon. This theyr ambicy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they wyll to be confyrmed &amp; eſtablyſſhed euen of the ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, that be departed out of this worlde. But this example came from the deuyll, as ſure as god lyueth in heuen. For ſo that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane ſpirite is wonte to worke, and to do his buſyneſſe by vyſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of deed folke,
<note place="margin">Wyſyons of deade men.</note> that he my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte make men madde, and to make them affrayed. This is <pb facs="tcp:6697:16"/>vndoubted, &amp; of a very ſuretye, that patryarches and kynges in the olde teſtament dyd ſomtyme fyght and handle weapons: but that was onely for the worde of god, &amp; for his peoples cauſe, by the teſtymony of ſcrypture. But it pleaſeth our lordes of Miſnia &amp; the blynde ſee of Rome, to call all that myracles, what ſoeuer doth fortifye &amp; mayntayne tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall honoures and ryches / yea moreouer I do thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke this thyng alſo in a maner to be but a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged &amp; fayned thynge, (lykewyſe as al the myracles are well nere, which are reherſed in all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bulle) that the Pope with the Miſnia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes by ſuche maner leaſynges &amp; erroure wolde put good Benno to martyrdome, that not onelye they myght haue a confeſſour of Benno,
<note place="margin">Benno a martyr.</note> but alſo a martyr. For yf <pb facs="tcp:6697:16"/>he was a good &amp; vertuous man, it is vndoubted that they do put hym vnto greatter puniſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, than euer was any martyr put vnto. For with what contumely &amp; rebuke coulde he be more foule blotted &amp; ſtayned, than this that he is ſayde to haue lyued other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe than the goſpell dothe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che / and that thoſe vyſyons are aſcrybed vnto hym, whiche euen the deuyll hym ſelfe is wonte to handle? Howe moche more wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome than ſhuld it haue ben for you, O you worſhypfull Miſni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anes, to haue kepte you ſtyll at home with your Benno &amp; ſuche maner myracles? And I wolde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayle you, and aduertyſe you to be more ware and more wyſe hereafter, and not to contynewe &amp; holde on with ouer many ſuche folyſſhe and peuyſſhe thynges <pb facs="tcp:6697:17"/>to dyſhonoure &amp; blaſpheme god. For here you do ſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> youre boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, eyther is but forged and vntrue: or els doubtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Benno is dampned. And yf it be ſo, that you do holde on with obſtynate myndes to ronne hedlonge, and to mayntayne and defende your lyes, or ſo open &amp; many feſte vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Benno: than am I inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from your bloode, and from the bloode of all thoſe, which do take parte with you. It myghte ſeme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you haue hytherto moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ynough &amp; more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ynough / and that it is tyme ones to take vp with ſuche thynges. And the other miracles are ſo vayne, and ſo nothing worthe and very try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles: that the thynge is worthye to be petyed becauſe I wyll not ſpeake here, that blynde men are ſoone and eaſely begyled, &amp; they <pb facs="tcp:6697:17"/>whiche are redy to tell and here lyes. For who I pray you wolde not laugh at this, that the belles which were halowed of Benno, do dryue away tempeſtes of we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? as who ſhulde ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> other belles coulde not do the ſame, or as thoughe the deuyll, whiche coniured into a glaſſe doth ſuffre hym ſelfe to be ſent awaye agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, coulde not brynge in, &amp; chaſe awaye a tempeſt, that ſo by the permiſſyon &amp; ſufferaunce of god he may deceyue wretched men. For yf euery thynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is rare, ought the ſame forthwith to be a myracle comen from heuen: than ſhulde there neuer any falſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle be done any where. Of whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſorte is this alſo, that Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no went beyonde Albi, &amp; was ſene in this place &amp; that place, bothe at one tyme. Who knoweth, I <pb facs="tcp:6697:18"/>pray you whether this were Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, or els ſome deuyll? For howe many tymes hathe the deuyll played ſuche prankes? For howe harde a thynge, or howe great a mayſtrye ſhall it be, thynke you, to the deuyll,
<note place="margin">The pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of this worlde.</note> whiche is prynce of this worlde, to make feble, or to bewytch any man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is his owne all redye throughe vnbelefe in Chryſt, and afterwarde to bydde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde hym to be ledde vnto ſome ſaynte, where he may be delyuered and rydde from his dyſeaſe or euyll? And than this thynge ſtreyght wayes ſhall be aſcrybed god wotte, vnto y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. But O good lorde, howe vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpectelye &amp; vnwyſely do we al thinges? Howe raſſhely &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduyſedly do we ronne on forthe as it were certayne blynde men? Howe pyteouſlye dyd the deuyll <pb facs="tcp:6697:18"/>deceyue ſaynte Gregorye in his dyaloges?
<note place="margin">Saynte Gregory.</note> For there is in euery place ſo moche plentye of ſuche maner iuggelyng caſtes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes, whiche he hath exercyſed, &amp; yet doth exercyſe, that I coulde of them make tenne other ſuche ſayntes, as Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no is / who agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne can ſufficye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proue, that the holye fountayne was broughte forthe by Benno: ſauyng onely that the comon opynyon goeth ſo aboute of it? For a man may fynde many lyke thyngꝭ / the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and origynall cauſe wherof is ſtraunge and vnknowen / of which ſorte there are many thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges at Rome. Brieffely, who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer wyll deſcrybe and ymagine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good lyfe of an holy byſſhop: He ought of neceſſyte to brynge forthe the wordes and doctryne,
<note place="margin">Sygnes of true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe.</note> wherin he was excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And alſo <pb facs="tcp:6697:19"/>faythe, charyte and the croſſe of perſecucyon whiche was layde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his backe for his doctrynes ſake. Theſe thynges onely are the true tokens of an holy man / But nowe this bulle ſaythe in dede, that Benno dyd preache: but what he dyd preache, or what he dyd vtterly beleue, it maketh no mencyon at all / neyther is there ſo moche as any mencyon at al made of charyte, and of the croſſe / onely it ſpeketh of his ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonyes, &amp; howe that in great angre he ranne away &amp; afflycted and vexed certayne men for the goodes of the churche. Beſydes this there is caryed aboute tales of certayne ſpirites and phanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes or ymagynacions of vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne and fayned myracles, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſhulde nede moche more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacion, whether they dyd chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce <pb facs="tcp:6697:19"/>accordynglye and verely or not, than this, whether Benno be a ſaynte or not. But this thynge myght eaſely be perſwaded vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, that Benno in dede was a good man, but yet was in many thyngꝭ ſeduced and deceyued of the Pope:
<note place="margin">Benno ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duſed and begyled.</note> and yet neuertheleſſe at the laſte throughe the vnme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable mercy of god was ſaued in lyke maner as it hathe chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Bernarde, &amp; to very many other electe &amp; choſen perſones. But that he dyd ſuche myracles, or wrought ſuche folyſſhe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as the bulle doth aſſygne &amp; aſcrybe vnto hym: I ſuppoſe no man ſhall proue / or at the leaſte wyſe yf he can proue it: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they do make Benno the chylde of dampnacyon, and heyre of helle / for aſmoche as his lyfe is cleane repugnaunt and contrary to the <pb facs="tcp:6697:20"/>goſpell. Wherfore, as for my parte, I wolde gyue counſayle, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhulde be any whytte moued or ſtyrred with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecracyon or canonyſacyon: but rather that good Benno ſhulde be lefte quyete and in reſt to the iudgement of god, which aboue dothe knowe what is done with Benno, and what condycyon &amp; ſtate he is in / For theſe myracles do proue nothynge at all. More ouer euen his very doctryne alſo ſemeth to haue ben cleane repug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunt &amp; contrary to faythe, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie, and the croſſe / what neded than this ſo great canoniſacyon of hym: ſyth it forceth lytle, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be made a ſaynte or not. For euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be a chryſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſaued, all thoughe neyther Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no, neyther yet any other ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made a ſaynt: (to paſſe ouer <pb facs="tcp:6697:20"/>and ſpeake no worde here that it can not be, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lucre is ſoughte here in this thynge. I aſte of all, yf it be ſo, that for all theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche we haue hytherto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyted, yet thou arte not perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded good louynge reader: at the leaſt wyſe the very bulle it ſelfe, (yf I be not begyled) wyll per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the, in whiche the Pope hym ſelfe doth confeſſe &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, that he hym ſelfe with his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes dyd make theyr prayers vnto god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde not ſuffre them to erre in this buſyneſſe. Here I beſeche, ſe and conſydre thyne owne ſelfe, howe the pope dothe lye vnto vs:
<note place="margin">The falſe lye of the Pope.</note> and howe throughe ouermoche deſyre and ſtudy to begyle other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth begyle his owne ſelfe. For yf he do pray, that god wyll not ſuffre hym to erre in declarynge &amp; pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſſhing <pb facs="tcp:6697:21"/>of Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no to be a ſaynt: Howe can he, I beſeche you, be aſſured and out of doubt? Howe can he ꝓue, that his prayer was herde, and his peticyon graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? What aungell dyd appere to hym, &amp; ſhewe hym this thyng, that he myghte be aſſured of it? But ſome ſuche thynge it muſte nedes haue ben, ſeynge that he dothe here preſcrybe a newe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycle of the fayth: which thynge to do, is as laufull to hym, &amp; as moche auctoryte he hathe to do it, as I haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de heuen and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne. On the other ſyde agayne, whan he reporteth and recyteth ſo ofte, that by the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles he was certyfyed and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of his holynes: wherfore I praye you dothe he aſke coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle of god, concernynge that thynge, whereof he was all redye <pb facs="tcp:6697:21"/>aſſured? doſte thou not thynke, that this is to tempte god, and to ſcorne hym: whan thou doſte aſke &amp; deſyre to knowe a thynge, which thou haſte perfyte know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of all redy? But after this faſſhyon and maner the deuyll is wonte to ſhame hym ſelfe / for lyes can not agre nor ſtande to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyther, but they muſte nedes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes impugne theym ſelfes. Lykewyſe as this our pope,
<note place="margin">The inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtancye of the Pope.</note> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he goeth about to worke moſt holylye and wyttely, calleth vpon god, and deſyreth to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed: and in ſo doynge ſheweth hym ſelfe to be in doubt and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſured, where as yet before he hath concluded it to be certayne and vndoubted, &amp; alſo wylleth it to be taken for vndoubted / no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge pceyuyng nor markyng, that whyles he prayeth &amp; deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb facs="tcp:6697:22"/>to be certyfyed, he dothe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowlege and confeſſe hym ſelfe to be vnaſſured and in doubt. It is therfore certayne &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that he dothe lye, eyther wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he doth praye, or els at the leaſte whan he dothe make his ſaynt. And he lyeth loude and with full mouthe, as the comen ſayeng is / For he dothe but onelye make a countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and ſemblaunce of prayer: and in verye dede dothe mocke and ſcorne god. Howe be it in that he doth praye as vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, he prayeth truthe. But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne on the other ſyde he lyeth whan he ſaythe that he is certy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed &amp; aſſured by myracles. For aſmoche than as this matter is handeled and done by mere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes and lyes / by blyndyng of mennes iyes, and ſubtylte: it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth, that thou, who ſoeuer <pb facs="tcp:6697:22"/>thou art, do beware of this newe Idole, whiche vſurpeth &amp; taketh vpon hym the name of Benno / whome yf thou wylte not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe and acknowlege for a ſaynte, at the leaſte wyſe let it greue the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we do comenlye ſo folyſſhe and ſo chyldyſſhely abuſe deed men,
<note place="margin">We abuſe deed men.</note> that by them we do caſte downe hedlonge the wretched kynde of men into myſchiefe / what ſhall Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no do, yf we do vſe his bones and his relyques to Idolatrye, for cauſe to wraſt out money fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſtruccyon of ſo many ſoules? wherfore as concernyng theſe thyngꝭ, let this ſuffyce that hathe ben ſpoken hereto of vs.</p>
               <p>Nowe let vs ſpeke of the verye ryght and true canonyſacyon, &amp; whiche is the ſure, vndoubted, &amp; holſome conſecracyon and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of a ſaynte. Fyrſt of all it <pb facs="tcp:6697:23"/>is to be conſydered and marked, that the ſcripture doth make but ſmall mencyon, or els none at all any where of ſayntes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen:
<note place="margin">Sayntes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> but onely of thoſe ſayntes &amp; holy men that are conuerſaunt &amp; abydynge here in erthe, as ſaynt Paule doth wryte to the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xii. chapytre. Gyue pte of your goodes to releue the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſytie &amp; nede of ſayntes. And in the .v. chapytre. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt epyſtle to Timothe. yf ſhe ſhall haue waſſhed the fete of ſayntes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd to make an ende i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fewe wordes, Paule in all his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyſtles calleth them ſayntes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whome he wryteth / ſhewynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery chryſten man in his lyfe is a ſaynt. But the Papiſtes do knowe no ſaynte ſauynge onely thoſe whiche are in heuen: and <pb facs="tcp:6697:23"/>whome they do dayly ſette in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and for this cauſe doubtles they do not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, and do depyſe and haue in contempte all the verye ſayntes of god. yf than we wyll make our lyfe to agree with the rule of the ſcrypture: we ought to bryng awaye our ſelfes from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes whiche are in heuen, &amp; to tourne our ſelfes vnto them that are in erthe / we oughte to extolle theſe ſayntes, and theſe we oughte to honoure. This thynge, no doubt of it, is pleaſaunte and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto god, whiche hathe alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the ſame. For as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge them that are depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of this worlde, he hathe gyuen vs no commaundement at all: wherfore it is not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table nor pleaſaunte vnto hym, what ſoeuer it be,
<note place="margin">Idolatry</note> that we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe
<pb facs="tcp:6697:24"/>vpon them / For this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Idolatrye hathe ben inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of men, becauſe this thynge dothe brynge in ſome lucre / as other men before me haue ſufficy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ently declared, and haue largely treated of all this matter. For hytherto I haue wrytten no ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyall thynge as yet of the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyon of ſayntes, (which thyng alſo certayne of my bokꝭ do wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) all thoughe it be imputed to me, and layed to my charge, as though I had ben y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authour and fyrſt begynner. And who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath ben the authour by the pleaſure &amp; wyll of god, of a ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye he dothe not myſtyke nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe me, neyther dothe it greue me to beare ꝑte of another mans diſhonoure and rebuke / to paſſe ouer in the meane ſeaſon, that I do not coueyte to chalenge ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <pb facs="tcp:6697:24"/>mans wrytynges for myne, but I do acknowledge (as ryghte is) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god dothe alſo worke ſome thynge by other men, becauſe I wyll not ſeme to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buſynes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, all my ſelfe alone. It is euydente therfore, howe many thynges, and howe great coſte &amp; labour is neceſſarely required to the makynge of ſayntes as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge theyr bodyes:
<note place="margin">The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge of ſayntes, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyoned in the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</note> &amp; agayne on the other ſyde howe eaſye and howe redy a thyng that true wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhippyng of ſayntes is / which is ſpirytuall, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to wytte ſuche as Paule doth wryte to the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in the .xv. Chapytre. whan he ſaythe.</p>
               <p>Gyue parte of your goodes to the neceſſyte of ſayntes / &amp; agay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne preuente eche one of you ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with honoure / agayne lette euery man eſteme another man <pb facs="tcp:6697:25"/>at more than he dothe eſteme his owne ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THis onely is to worſhyppe ſayntes duely to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorye &amp; honoure of god. For in aſmoche as we are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of god, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to ſubmytte hym ſelfe to his neyghboure, and to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe god in that te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple / to gyue place vnto hym / to loue hym / to deale kyndly and louyngly with hym / and yf he may at any tyme, to prouoke hym vnto better thin ges. Nowe theſe thyngꝭ are not done (I ſuppoſe) with ſhouelles or ſpades couered with ſyluer, nor yet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gylte rakes. And wold god thoſe men whiche do conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate and canonyſe Benno with the other ſayntꝭ, wold here gyue eare vnto me, &amp; wold ſuffre them ſelfes to be moniſſhed with theſe <pb facs="tcp:6697:25"/>wordes: Tell me who knoweth, whether theſe thynges be true or not? Doubtles this thynge can not be denyed, that al that coſtly ordenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and all that expence, and all that labour with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and veneracyon, &amp; brefely what ſoeuer ſuch maner thynge ſhall be beſtowed in Miſnia, is neyther ſo wel beſtowed nor is ſo acceptable vnto god: as it ſhuld be yf any man dyd gyue vnto a poore chryſten man a dyner or a garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Ye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thynge is rather vn pleaſaunte vnto almyghty god &amp; is honourynge of the deuyll: and this thynge is ſpirytuallye acceptable to god, and hatefull to the deuyll. For god hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded this thinge, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge he dothe not knowe at all. Howe many thouſandes of ducates, doſt thou ſuppoſe or <pb facs="tcp:6697:26"/>thynke, that Benno hathe coſre, beſydes that he ſhal coſt in tyme to come: with whiche (beynge caſt awaye euery one of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god, not without his great indy gnacyon &amp; angre) ſo many very ſayntes myghte haue ben holpen and fedde / doſte thou not ſuppoſe, that god with his aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels wyll tourne them ſelfes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that place, where ſome good man the ſame day had pytie and compaſſyon of ſome chryſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beynge in neceſſytie or afflyccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and wyll leaue Miſnia behynde theyr backe, where Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no is tour mented and afflycted: I wolde haue ſayd is made a ſaynt? wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall we ones begyn to be wyſe? Howe often tymes ſhall we nede to repete one thynge? why doſte thou not euen by comen reaſon lerne, whether it is better to do <pb facs="tcp:6697:26"/>almes vpon poore ſayntes that are a lyue: or els vpon this, that ſome man that deed is myght be made a ſaynte, whiche hathe no nede at all of ſuche humanytie &amp; kyndnes? And yf it be better and more profytable: to beſtowe it vpon poore lyuynge creatures: why are we ſuche nygardes &amp; ſo ſcaſe in layeng forth of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney here in this thynge:
<note place="margin">A folyſſhe and dyſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred libera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lytie.</note> and ſo prodygal &amp; lauyſſhe in the other thynge? But certaynely the iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes of god are vpryght &amp; ryghtuous / that is to wytte, that where it dothe greue vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe tenne florence frelye &amp; for nought vpon the very ſayntes, which thynge ſhulde be moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable and pleaſaunte to god: that there the deuyll ſhuld make vs ſo madde with the ſpiryte of Gedynes, and ſhulde ſo handell <pb facs="tcp:6697:27"/>vs that we do not doubte waſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye to beſtowe golden ſpades and rakes, yea and otherwhyles a thouſande flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes vpon deed mennes bones, and beſydes this to ſeche and purchaſe vnto our ſelfes al kynde and maner of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamytie and indygnacyon. But wretches haue neyther delyte to here theſe thynges, neyther to be leue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But be it ſo / yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it can not be auoyded, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we muſt nedes ones here &amp; haue experyence of it: thoughe we do neuer ſo moche put of from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to morowe / We do ſeche ſhame, and therfore we ſhal alſo fynde ſhame and rebuke, whiche verylye is euen nowe at hande. Beſydes this (to adde this alſo) though thoſe thynges alſo were true, whiche are reported of the ſygnes and myracles of Benno,
<pb facs="tcp:6697:27"/>and that the ſayd myracles were of effecte &amp; wrought of god hym ſelfe by Be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no, though theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles (I ſaye) were wroughte euen for the goſpell ſake, ſo as Chryſt dothe promyſe in the laſt chapitre of Marke: (which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge in very dede can neuer be ꝓued) yet for all that, we oughte not ſo folyſſhely, ſo raſſhely, nor with ſo madde a begynnyng to leape forthe ſo haſtelye to conſecrate &amp; canonyſe ſayntes. For ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſygnes &amp; myracles thoughe they do neuer ſo moche declare the holyneſſe of a mannes lyfe / before the workynge of them: yet can they not aſſure vs &amp; put vs out of doubt, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame man dyd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tynewe ſtedfaſt and holye alſo in his deth or els not.
<note place="margin">The iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gementes of god.</note> For aſmoche as the iudgemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of god are hydde &amp; vtterlye <pb facs="tcp:6697:28"/>meruaylous and dredefull / For he hym ſelfe ſayth in the .vii. cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre of Mathewe.</p>
               <p>Many men ſhall ſaye to me, lorde haue we not in thy name caſte forthe deuylles &amp; wrought many myraclas? And than I ſhall anſwere vnto theym. Go from me you workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THeſe forſoth are farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; more ſure &amp; vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted myracles, than are thoſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che Benno hathe wrought / and Chryſte alſo dothe acknowlege them: yet for all that he doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne the perſones by whome they were wrought. To the ſame effecte and purpoſe. Moyſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dothe wryte in the .xiii. chapy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytre of Deuteronomium, that god dothe permytte and ſuffre <pb facs="tcp:6697:28"/>myracles to be wrought by falſe prophetes, to thentent to tempte and proue his people.
<note place="margin">Falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes.</note> Wherfore it maketh nothynge to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, though any ſaynt do worke myracles after his deathe at his graue / For who knoweth whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther god doth proue vs and trye our faythe by thoſe myracles, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy man i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the meane ſeaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge condempned at the tyme of his dethe. Lykewyſe as were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe ꝓphetes in theyr lyfe tyme. But in eſpecyall this is a ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecte thynge, whan thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles are wroughte to thende, that throughe theym holye lyfe in dede may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended: but not that the faythe and worde of god maye be confyrmed. And ſuche for the mooſt parte are all the myracles of this Benno, of which there is nothynge that <pb facs="tcp:6697:29"/>dothe appertayne to the confyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy on of the word of god, but onelye to his ceremonyes, his prayours / to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gloryes &amp; boſtes of the churche of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Miſnianes / and fynally to the pompes and auctoryte &amp; power of the church of Rome / Do you not thynke it to be an excellente myracle, that Balaam (as it is wryten in the.
<note place="margin">Balaam.</note> xxiiii. chapytre of Numeri) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he wolde or not was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to preache the worde of god, and to blyſſe the chyldren of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell? Was it not alſo a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayle that Saul dyd prophecye amonge the prophetes?
<note place="margin">1. Regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; Saul.</note> dothe it folowe therfore, that they muſte nedes be ſayntes: yf the holye ghoſte dyd ſpeake or dyd worke ſuche maner thynges by them? Wherfore before thextreme iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought of chryſten <pb facs="tcp:6697:29"/>men to be iudged &amp; called a ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as ſaynte Paule dothe teache in the .iiii. chapitre of the fyrſt epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell to the Corinthianes whan he ſaythe.</p>
               <p>Do not iudge any thynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tyme vntyll y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſhal come, whiche ſhall brynge to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte the thynges that are hydde in darkenes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>SPirytually ſyth we do know that Chryſt and Paule haue prophecyed before, that in theſe laſte dayes ſo goodly &amp; ſo gaye painted myracles ſhuld be done, that euen the verye electe &amp; cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen perſones, yf it were poſſyble, ſhulde be begyled.
<note place="margin">We ought to haue good opy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyon of ſayntes.</note> Nothynge dothe lette, but that we may of a ſymple and a playne mynde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt them for ſayntes, &amp; iudge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one chryſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought <pb facs="tcp:6697:30"/>to thynke and iudge of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chryſten man: But it is in no wyſe to be receyued or ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that we wyll be as ſure of it as of an artycle of the faythe and hange vpon it, ſo as the pope tyrannouſly with his Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no dothe requyre: ſauynge one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peraduenture of thoſe whome god in ſcrypture hathe decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and pronounſed to be ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / of whiche ſorte are the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryarkes, the prophetes, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtelles, and the dyſcyples. I do with a good wyll beleue, that Elyſabeth whiche was buryed at Magbrughe is a ſaynte. I beleue the very ſame alſo of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne, of Hierome, of Ambro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, of Bernarde, &amp; of Fraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſke: but yet ſo that I wyll not leane and grounde vpon this be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lefe, <pb facs="tcp:6697:30"/>and defende it to the dethe. For the certentie and the groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewarke of our faythe oughte to be fetched at the ſcrypture,
<note place="margin">The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentye of our fayth.</note> and to be taken out of it. And excepte it be expreſſyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: neyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope, no nor yet any Aungelles haue any power to make ſo moche as onelye one artycle of the faythe. But hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto we haue ſpoken ſuffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye agaynſt the deuylyſſhe worke: Nowe it remayneth to ſpeake ſomwhat beſydes, aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynſt the deuylyſſhe wordes / to thentente that the ſayde worke may be ſette forthe to the comen people as it were in a table, and ſo at the laſte be dyſprayſed. For I am not ygnoraunt, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſermones ſhall be made eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where throughe out Miſnia, <pb facs="tcp:6697:31"/>and with what crafte they ſhall mocke and begyle the people, to make them ſette moche by theyr Idole, and to open theyr purſes wyde vnto blyſſed Benno / that is to wytte to the profyte and be hofe of theyr owne belye / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore here I do faythfully &amp; with a chryſten mynde (as I am bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to do) exhorte and monyſſhe all men, as many as ſhal be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at ſuche ſermones: that they do not conſydre onelye the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde apparaunce and the dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guyſed face of the thynge, but rather the thyng it ſelfe / and the verye foundacyon and grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de / I can geſſe well ynoughe what maner roten fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacyon of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they wyll laye vnder theyr deceytefull and falſe buyldyng, and ſuche one dothe the byſſhop of Miſnia begynne to boſt euen <pb facs="tcp:6697:31"/>nowe in his wrytynge, theffecte wherof is this. Laudate dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m in ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctis ſuis. That is to ſay, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe you god in his ſayntes. Theſe laudes and prayſynges doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les they do ſtretch out very farre bothe in lengthe and bredthe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrmynge alſo that this is lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and prayſynge of god in his ſayntes, yf they be canony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and called vpon by the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of men. But thou who ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer thou arte whiche doſte here theſe ſermones, I praye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, yea &amp; knowe thou for a verye certentie, that thou hereſt a lye, &amp; the prynce and father of al lyes, whoſe propretie is to paruerte y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures &amp; the worde of god. For this place maketh agaynſt the in aſmoche as it is taken of the olde teſtament, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye no ſaynt was yet in heuen &amp; <pb facs="tcp:6697:32"/>prayed vnto, but alſo it was co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, that god onely ſhulde be called vpon and onely prayed vnto, as hym ſelfe dothe wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the. xlix. pſalme ſayenge.</p>
               <p>Calle vpon me in the daye of trybulacyon, and I ſhal delyuer the / and thou ſhalte honour me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd therfore he wylleth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo it to be preached of hym, that he is the ſauyour of men, as it is wrytten in the .iiii. chapytre of the fyrſte epyſtle to Timothe / and he doth alſo wytneſſe in the xxxv. pſalme hym ſelfe to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued bothe of men and alſo of beaſtes. Wherfore helthe &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uacyon ought to be aſked and de ſyred of none other, ſauyng one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye of hym. Moreouer this pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſerypture dothe not ſpeke of holye men or of holy women, <pb facs="tcp:6697:32"/>but rather of holye places / for thus it is redde after the verytie of the Hebrue texte. Laudate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum in ſancto vel in ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio ſuo, that is to ſay / prayſe you the lorde in his ſanctuarye or in his holy and deuoute place: Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kewyſe as it is wrytten in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xix.
<note place="margin">The pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the pſalme. Laudate dominum in ſanctis eius, is de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared &amp; expounꝭ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded.</note> pſalme. Emittat tibi auxiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de ſancto / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſay, helpe mought he ſende the from his holy place, and agayne in the .xxi. pſalme. Tu autem in ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto habitas, that is to ſay, thou dwelleſt in a holy place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd lykewyſe in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places which are eaſy to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de here and there in the ſcrypture. And in theſe wordes he wylleth vs to expreſſe &amp; fulfyl the maner of honouryng of god, whiche was exercyſed and vſed <pb facs="tcp:6697:33"/>in the olde teſtament by the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites and ſyngynge men with ſonges and belles, as it is wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the fyrſte boke of Parali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pomenon the .xv. chapitre. Syth than it is ſo, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nowe in the newe teſtamente there is no place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted vnto vs of god, but we our ſelfes are the temple of god, as Paule wytneſſeth in the .iii. chapytre of the fyrſt epyſtle to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians / and Chryſte hym ſelfe alſo in the. iiii. chapytre of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe take awaye all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripte and determynate places, whan he ſayth. The tyme ſhall come whan you ſhal worſhyppe the father neyther here in Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, but in ſpiryte &amp; trouthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>THeſe wordes therfore muſt be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de now in theſe dayes of a ſpirytuall ſanctuary, <pb facs="tcp:6697:33"/>ſo that Laudate dominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto ſuo, is aſmoche to ſaye, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge vs, and in the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon and companye of Chryſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / wherfore it can not be wreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nor applyed to the canonyſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of ſayntes, or to the callyng vpon them by prayour. And yf bycauſe of this place it myghte be proued and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are to be canoniſed or prayed vnto: than by the ſame reaſon belles, ſymballes, taberettes, &amp; harpes, ſhulde be made ſayntes &amp; prayed vnto. For it foloweth in the ſame pſalme.</p>
               <p>Prayſe the lorde in ſhrylle ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge ſymballes, prayſe hym in harpes and organes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>GO to than nowe, yf thou doſt prayſe god in theſe mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſycall inſtrumentes: praye alſo <pb facs="tcp:6697:34"/>vnto them, &amp; make them ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / as that Miſnicall &amp; Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall wrytte dothe teache vs by this place of the ſcrypture. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m in ſanctis ſuis. For I lyſte not here to reherſe, leſte I myghte ſeme to tedyous, howe thoſe men for the moſt parte are not wonte to prayſe god in his ſayntes, which do honour ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and do praye vnto them: but contrarye wyſe do farre dyſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure and blaſpheme god / For they do put theyr hope and theyr truſte in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes / which thyng what is it els, than to forſake the faythe / to denye god / and to ſet vp the ſayntes for an Idole? of whiche mater we haue ſuffycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entlye treated in another place They allege alſo that place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xv. chapitre of Iob. Voca et ad aliquem ſanctorum conuertere / that <pb facs="tcp:6697:34"/>that is to ſaye. Call,
<note place="margin">The place of Iob, is evpouned and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> and tourne the to ſome of the ſayntes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>FOr thoſe papiſtes are ſo blyn de and ſo folyſſhe hardy that yf it happen them to fynde this worde, ſancti, in any place: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they wyll forthwith confyrme and eſtablyſſhe the veneracyons and merytes of ſayntes, euen as ryghtfully as they go aboute to proue purgatorye, yf in any pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce they do fynde this worde fyre or this worde purgatorye / or els to proue holye water, yf they may fynde this worde water in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture. But as for this pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of Iob, vnderſtande it thus, that Elyphas dothe reproue the good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iob of ſynne euen for this cauſe, that god had punyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed hym / for he ſaythe.</p>
               <p>Call, I beſeche the, euen one <pb facs="tcp:6697:35"/>and loke about vnto ſome of the ſayntes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>AS who ſhulde ſaye / God neuer punyſſhed any holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / neyther canneſt thou ſhewe that euer any of the ſayntes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ben afflycted, whiche waye ſoeuer thou do tourne the. But ſeynge that god dothe punyſſhe the ſo ſore: it is vndoubted that thou arte no holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but a wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and a ſynfull man. Here I beſeche the conſydre howe gayly they haue wreſted theſe wordes to the veneracyon of ſayntes. They haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderacyon nor no regarde in the worlde vnto any maner thynge, but what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they haue thought and put poſed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr owne mynde: there is no remedye but that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge muſte nedes ſtrayte wayes for <pb facs="tcp:6697:35"/>theyr pleaſure be contayned in the ſcrypture. The thyrde place is the .xx. chapytre of the prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes. It is ruyne and deſtruccion to a man for to deuoure a ſaynt, and afterwarde to ſeche vowes / the wordes in laten are theſe. Ruina eſt homini deuorare ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, et poſtea querere vota.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>HEre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of this worde deuorare they do rede deuo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tare, to thentent that ſo (yf god be pleaſed) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auctoryte of ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſhulde be eſtablyſſhed. But the true texte, &amp; as the Authour left it, is this Laqueus eſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni exprobrare rem ſacra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et poſt ea vota q<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rere. That is to ſaye it is a ſtumbelynge ſtocke &amp; ſure &amp; vndoubted deſtruccy on to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to corrupte &amp; pollute holye thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and holye wordes, and than <pb facs="tcp:6697:36"/>afterwardꝭ to deſyre to be acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted holye becauſe of his ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyes, ſacryfyces, &amp; workꝭ. As for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſtes, whiche whan they do pſecute y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god, &amp; what ſoeuer thynge els is holy i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede: yet neuertheles they do in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane ſeaſon ſay maſſes, &amp; do many good dedꝭ, thynkyng nothyng at all to chaunge theyr wycked ſtate of lyuynge, &amp; ones to make an ende to deſtroye and deuoure holy thyngꝭ. But nowe whan they are broughte to that poynte that they can not by the auctoryte of ſcripture i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any wyſe proue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayntes are to be prayed vnto, or to be accompted for me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyatours, but cleane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary the ſcrypture dothe proue &amp; fortyfye that there is none other medya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour or interceſſoure, than that onely medyatour &amp; interceſſoure
<pb facs="tcp:6697:36"/>Chryſt Ieſu,
<note place="margin">Chryſte.</note> as Paule doth tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> many other places, but ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytually in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .iii. &amp; .v. chapi. to the Romanes, &amp; in the .ii. chap. of the fyrſt epyſtell to Timothe, they yet (as beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth valyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te men) do not gyue ouer theyr hold, but do ſech ſome way, by which they may eſcape out, &amp; put by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfꝭ. For this word mediator (ſay they) is taken two maner wayes / one waye it is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for a ſatyſfactory mediator / or a ſatiſfactor. Another waye it is taken for an interceſſorye me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyatour or an interceſſor. Nowe to ſpeake of a ſatyſfactory medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator or meane, there is but onely one / that is to wytte Chryſte, whiche hathe ſatiſfyed for vs / but the ſayntes (after theyr myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des) ſhall be accompted inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorye mediatours. Nowe yf <pb facs="tcp:6697:37"/>any man do aſke of them, where theſe thynges are had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, than forthwith they lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs the auctoryte of holye churche,
<note place="margin">The chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che.</note> that is to wytte of theyr owne ſelfꝭ, whome y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſte doth not ſuffre to erre any thyng at all. Theſe men (ſaye they) are of this opynyon and do thynke thus, ergo it is thus: (howe be it yf they ſhulde playe the fooles thus in theyr ſcoles, it ſhulde be called petitio principii) wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought to proue that ſayntes are mediatours, whiche the ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dothe in no place teache. But yet neuertheleſſe they procede forthe on / &amp; euen as thoughe the mater were nowe proued and knowen for vndoubted, they do of theyr owne brayne ymagyne two kyndes or ſortes of medya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. Therfore whan thou hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt <pb facs="tcp:6697:37"/>any ſuch maner thyng: thou mayſte well knowe the wolfe by his voyce.
<note place="margin">The holy ghoſte.</note> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſte tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth nothyng, which is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcrypture / as Chryſt ſaythe.</p>
               <p>He ſhall teache you al thynges and he ſhall brynge into your re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>membraunce all thynges, what ſoeuer I haue ſayd vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd ſo at lengthe it ſhall be made open and manyfeſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this tragedy whiche is played concernynge Benno in Miſnia is played onelye by mere lyes &amp; deceytes, of the deuyll bothe in wordes and alſo in dedes / wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore loke thou that thou do take hede to thy ſelfe, and thinke thus in thy mynde / thoughe we do graunte alſo theſe thynges to be true and vndoubted, yet that not <pb facs="tcp:6697:38"/>withſtandyng ſyth it is a thynge not greatly profytable, and whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thou mayſte be without full well, ſe that thou do kepe thy mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney to the releuyng and helpyng of thy chyldren and of poore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, whiche haue pryncypallye nede therof / and vpon whome it ſhal be beſt beſtowed. But nowe moche more thou oughteſt to do this, ſythe it is euydent and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted, that this thynge is not onely vnprofytable, but alſo fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely fayned, deceyteful &amp; playnly deuelyſſhe / yea co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſydre and loke well vpon the faſſhyon of them thyne owne ſelfe (yf thou wylte) whiche yf they dyd any thyng at all vnfaynedly and hartelye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende and ſeche the hououre and glorye of god &amp; of ſayntes: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt they ſhulde fynde mo than two thouſande occaſyons <pb facs="tcp:6697:38"/>by whiche they myghte ſuccoure and releue theyr neyghboure / of whiche euery one ſhulde be ſyxe hundred tymes more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all that pompe &amp; royalte wherwith Benno was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlated and made a ſaynt. But nowe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that they dyſpyſynge theyr neyghbour and nothyng regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge his neceſſyte, are all togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſet vpon this thynge: euery man may eaſely perceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are blynde &amp; madde, and by the canoniſacyon of Benno do ſeche theyr owne profyte and glorye, &amp; thy money. How be it I do hope, that they are come after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme,
<note place="margin">Prouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes.</note> (as it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly ſaid in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe) and that they haue all in vayne ſpredde a nette before the byrdes iyes, as Salamon ſayth in the fyrſte chapytre of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbes. But yf thou wyll wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe <pb facs="tcp:6697:39"/>ſayntes duelye, &amp; prayſe them worthelye: thou ſhall do thynge as farre forthe as the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples of ſcryptures ſhall tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che &amp; preſcrybe vnto the,
<note place="margin">The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyppyng of ſayntꝭ.</note> of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſcriptures thou mayſte ſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what maner the grace &amp; the benefytes, whiche haue ben gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of god vnto the ſayntes, are propowned and layed forthe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore god, whether it be in peticy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or in thankes gyuynge, or els in complaynte / as for example. Moyſes prayeth in the .xxxiii. chapitre of Exodi, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth.</p>
               <p>Remembre Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, to whom thou haſte ſworne. &amp;c. And Salomon in the .xxxi. pſalme / lorde remembre Dauid, and all his calamytie. And Chryſt vpon the croſſe ſayd that verſe of the .xxi. pſalme.</p>
               <p>Our fathers haue hoped in the <pb facs="tcp:6697:39"/>and haue ben delyuered. But I am a worme. &amp;c. And in the .xlv. pſalme. O god we haue harde with our eares, and our fathers haue tolde vs the worke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſte wrought vpon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>ANd in many other places of the ſcrypture / here thou ſeyſte that no ſaynte is prayed vnto / but that god is prayſed in them, whiche dyd promyſe vnto them ſuch maner benefytes, and hathe fulfylled his promyſe: to thentent that he wolde moniſſhe and teache vs, that ſuche maner grace ought with all confydence to be aſked and hoped of hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone / vnto thobtaynyng wherof that faythfull and onely media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is ſuffycyent, yea &amp; more than ſuffycyent / that is to wytte, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chryſte of all ſayntes mooſt <pb facs="tcp:6697:40"/>holy. To whome onely, with the father, &amp; the holy ghoſte, be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe &amp; glorye for euermore. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Thus endeth the worke made agaynſt the falſe canonyſacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Benno the byſſhoppe.</p>
            <p>☞ Tranſlated and prynted in Englyſſhe, in the yere of our lorde god, a thouſande CCCCC.xxxiiii. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☜ ☞ ☜ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:40"/>
            <p>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge in ſaynt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyns paryſſhe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes charynge Croſſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☞ ☜</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:41"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of Robert Wyer</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6697:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
